Charles L. McCollough Collection 015
People's Archive, MLK Library
Charles L. McCollough Collection
1967-1999
People's Archive, MLK Library
McCollough, Charles L.
015
1.5 Linear feet
3 Boxes
Arrangement
Series 1: Correspondence Correspondence in this series consists of letters to Charles L. McCollough, letters to members of his family, and letters from members of his family. Series 2: Holy Land This collection consists of clippings, an itinerary, and memorabilia from Walter McCollough and family's trip to the Holy Land in 1967. It includes postcards and photographs. Series 3: Sermons This series contains sermons and notes used by Charles L. McCollough. The sermons are arranged alphabetically by their title or subject. Series 4: Outreach This series contains correspondence, memorabilia, meeting minutes, and other materials that show Chalres L. McCollough's work with both the United House of Prayer and Believers in Christ Ministries. Series 5: Programs This series contains programs from events that honored the McColloughs, were attended by the McColloughs, or were arranged by their organizations. Series 6: Awards This series includes awards given to Charles. L. McCollough or his organization. Series 7: Oversize This series includes oversize Outreach and Awards materials. They include photographs and certificates.
Biographical / Historical
Charles Leon McCollough was born in Washington, D.C. on March 12, 1941 to Bishop Walter McCollough and Clara B. McCollough. He graduated from Cardozo High School where he lettered in track. Mr. McCollough joined his father as a Minister at his father's church, the United House of Prayer for All People. His father, "Sweet Daddy" McCollough was the leader of a congregation that included millions of members around the country. Ordained in 1967, Mr. McCollough was a pastor at the United House of Prayer from 1975 to 1992. In 1991, Walter "Sweet Daddy" McCollough died and it was assumed that Mr. McCollough would ascend to Bishop of the House of Prayer. However, Mr. McCollough lost the election to S. C. Madison amid cries of a rigged election. Mr. McCollough filed a lawsuit challenging the results, but it was dismissed because it was an ecclesiastical matter. Mr. McCollough was subsequently stripped of his position as pastor in the United House of Prayer. Mr. McCollough continued to allege other abuses by Bishop Madison, including the swindling of property from his late father and the refusal of the church to allow his mother to be interred in her husband's mausoleum at Fort Lincoln Cemetery. Mr. McCollough, his wife Marjorie Colee, his son Charles, Jr., and daughter Marjorie Clarissa McCollough-Jackson established the Believers in Christ Ministries where they focused on working with struggling populations. Their work included Thanksgiving Baskets, toys at Christmas, tutoring programs, and anti-drugs programs. Mr. McCollough died on June 22, 1996 at the age of 55, of a heart attack, which he suffered after eulogizing his late nephew David Robinson. (Information taken from Obituary, Washington Post, June 28, 1996, C4.)
Custodial History
The collection was donated by Charles L. McCollough's widow, Marjorie C. McCollough in 1997.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of records that document the Ministry and life of Charles L. McCollough, Pastor of the United House of Prayer. Documents include: clippings, correspondence, speeches, sermons, meeting minutes and agendas, youth program information, certificates and awards, and photographs.
City churches; Religion; Clergy; Evangelicalism; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc); Correspondence; Minutes (Records); Speeches, addresses, etc; Ephemera
- Series 1: Correspondence
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence in this series consists of letters to C. L. McCollough, letters to members of his family and letters from members of his family.
  - Death of C. L. McCollough, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Rev. Edward Cooks, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Walter E. Fauntroy - Clergy Advisory Committee, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Fort Lincoln Cemetery: Mausoleum, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters from City Council, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Receipt for Telegram to MLK Jr. Family after Assassination, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Rabbi Jeffrey A. Wohlberg, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series 2: Holy Land
  This collection consists of clippings, an itinerary, and memorabilia from Walter McCollough and Family's trip to the Holy Land in 1967. It includes postcards and photographs.
  - Bishop Walter's Trip to Holy Land, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Christmas Card from the Holy Land, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Itinerary, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The Kibbutz, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photographs (two), 1967 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Postcards, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series 3: Sermons
  This series contains full sermons and sermon notes used by C. L. McCollough. The sermons are arranged alphabetically by their title or subject.
  - 17 Things Listed, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Christ Our Passover, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Continuing Adventure with God, Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cycles of Birth and Death, Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Death, Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - A Faith By Which to Die, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Funerals, Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - God is for Us, Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - God Will Provide, Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Habbuk the Profet, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Holy Ghost, Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Jehovah, Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Jesus and Death, Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Marshall Heights, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Motherhood, Undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - A Mother's Prayer, Undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Passover Season, Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Pronunciation Guide, Undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Romans Chapter Eight, Undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - The Shepherd's Prayer, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - There's Always a Springtime, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Wedding Vows, Undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - You Must be Identified, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Series 4: Outreach
  This series contains correspondence, memorabilia, meeting minutes, and other materials that show C. L. McCollough's work with both the United House of Prayer and Believers in Christ Ministries.
  - Apostle Charles L. McCollough Day, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Believers in Christ, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Children's Drawings for Rev. McCollough, Undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Clergy and Church Monitors District 6 and 7, Undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Clippings, 1991-1996 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Coalition of Concerned Clergy and Citizens of Ward 7, Undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Little Angel's and Youth Enrichment Program, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Minister's License, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Reinstatement of Pastor C. L. McCollough, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Richmond Crusaders, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Senior Minister Appointment, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - SHARE (photograph), Undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Student Assistance Program, Undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Student Report Cards, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Thanksgiving Baskets, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - United Way Payment, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Ward 7 Monthly Prayer Breakfast, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Series 5: Programs
  Series V contains programs from events that honored the McColloughs, were attended by the McColloughs, or were organized by their organizations.
  - Christian's Report Card, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Founder's Day, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Gala Holiday Reception and Buffet, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Marjorie-Poem, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Leon and Marjorie McCollough, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Rev. McCollough, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Rev. McCollough, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Rev. McCollough, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Rev. McCollough as Featured Speaker, 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Rev. McCollough Memorials, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Rev. McCollough Testimonial Service, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Men's Day Celebration, 1989-1992 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Pamphlets and Fliers, Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - SHARE DC, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Spring Revival Services, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Thanksgiving Day Celebration, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Thelonious Monk International Jazz Piano Competition, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - United House of Prayer Groundbreaking, 1979-1989 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Young People's Day, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Series 6: Awards
  The United House of Prayer, as well as, the City Council of Washington, DC and the National Organization of Free Masons gave the awards and Certificates in this series to C. L. McCollough or his organization.
  - Coalition of Concerned Citizenry in the Community, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Honor Roll Certificate, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Merit Award, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - School Attendance Certificates, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Top 100 "F" Class Achievement Award, 1977-1990 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Top 100 "G" Class Achievement Award, 1980-1990 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Top 100, 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Top Paying Individual/Pastor, 1978-1984 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - United House of Prayer Achievement Certificates, Undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Series 7: Oversize
  Oversize Outreach and Awards materials are found in this series. They include photographs and certificates.
  - Outreach, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Awards, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Awards, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Awards, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Awards, 1980-1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Awards, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Awards, 1982-1990 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Awards, 1979-1987 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Awards, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 9)